A hierarchical file system can be in a data set type called HFS or it can be in a ZFS data set.
HFS data sets can span many density volumes. If spanned, they must be SMS managed.
ZFS and HFS are both Unix file systems and both can participate in shared systplexes.
However, while HFS always has a single file system per data set,
ZFS can have multiple file systems in a single data set.
These data sets are called aggregates and are a collection of data sets.
HFS data sets are like PDSE data sets. They're allocated like any other ZOS data set.
Although an HFS data set is a ZOS data set and MVS open request fails,
users must use Unix system services to access data in such a data set.
The hierarchical file system consists of one root file system and multiple user file systems.
The root file system is the base for HFS and is at the top of the hierarchy.
HFS data sets are allocated as ZOS data sets, so DSN type equals HFS.
HFS data sets can only be opened by Unix system service kernel operations
and HFS data sets can reside on the same volumes as other ZOS data sets.
Non-SMS managed HFS data sets are often used.
Now, a few other characteristics. The size of the data set is limited to two gigabytes if single volume.
A multi-volume HFS can span up to a maximum of 59 volumes.
HFS can have up to a maximum of 123 extents per volume
and a multi-volume HFS can have up to a maximum of 255 total extents for all volumes.
Also, keep in mind that within a file system in HFS,
there is no way to control the amount of space each user can use.
It's actually possible for one user to use the entire space in a file system.
So the recommendation here is that each user have their own file system.
A ZFS aggregate is a VSAM linear data set or an LDS that contains one or more ZFS file systems.
The name of the aggregate is its VSAM LDS name.
A ZVS file system is a logical named entity contained within the ZVS aggregate
that has a root directory and can be mounted.
It has a logical maximum size known as its quota.
A ZFS file system is a named entity that resides in a ZFS aggregate.
It contains a root directory and can be mounted into the USS hierarchy.
File system is not really a new term, but a ZFS file system resides in a ZFS aggregate,
which is different from an HFS file system.
For compatibility mode aggregates, the VSAM LDS name is the same as the ZFS aggregate name,
is the same as the ZFS file system name.
The quota of these file systems is set to the size of the aggregate.
A compatibility mode aggregate can contain only one ZFS file system,
making this type of aggregate more like an HFS file system.
This is flagged in the aggregate when it's created.
Version file systems in a shared file system that are no longer being used
can be automatically unmounted.
Also, note that the multi-file system aggregates are no longer supported by ZOS.
A colony address space runs USS system code as an extension to the USS kernel address space.
ZFS runs as a Unix system services colony address space.
There must be an entry in a bpx-prm-palmlib member for ZVS,
and the ZVS proc must be available.
The bpx-palm member in the palmlib contains a file-sys type statement
for the ZVS physical file system.
It includes an AS name parameter specifying the ZFS proc.
AS name is required for PFSs that run in colony address spaces.
ZFS can now handle mounts of ZFS file systems contained in the bpx-palm.
Mount commands can be left in slash etc slash rc or moved into bpx-palm.
ZFS admin commands the query information, for example,
lsfs and aggrinfo can be issued by any user.
ZFS admin commands that modify, so for example,
ZFS admin create require that the user be logged in as root.
Now, what are the advantages of ZFS?
Well, ZFS is a file system that is fundamentally different from HFS.
The administration view of ZFS is different from HFS.
ZFS file systems are created in a different manner
from the way that HFS file systems are created.
But in general, however, the application view of ZFS is the same
as the application view of HFS.
The same APIs and commands are used for ZFS as are used for HFS.
Once the ZFS file system is mounted,
it's almost indistinguishable from a mounted HFS file system.
ZFS is a ZOS Unix file system that can be used in addition
to the hierarchical file system.
ZFS file systems contain files and directories that can be accessed
with the ZOS hierarchical file system
file application programming interfaces or APIs.
ZFS file systems can be mounted into the ZOS Unix hierarchy
along with other local or remote file system types,
for example, HFS, TFS, AutoMount, NFS, and so forth.
ZFS does not replace HFS, rather it's complementary to it.
And importantly, ZFS is the strategic Unix system services file system for ZOS.
Now, in the next video, we'll take a closer look
at using the HFS and ZFS file systems.
ZFS file systems contain file systems.